When something fades in the sun, it becomes history.
Saat sesuatu memudar di bawah mentari, itu jadi sejarah.
And when something soaks up the moonlight,
Dan saat sesuatu menyerap sinar bulan,
it becomes a myth.
itu menjadi mitos.
That means our story will become a myth.
Berarti kisah kita akan jadi mitos.
Well, we're being really romantic right now, you know.
Kita sangat romantis sekarang.
But why is it that I keep thinking about that thing?
Tapi kenapa aku terus pikirkan itu?
About what?
Apa?
The seafood noodles I told you about earlier.
Mi boga bahari yang kuceritakan.
I keep ruining the mood by thinking about how
Aku terus merusak suasana dengan memikirkan
there were 12 clams in the bowl of noodles.
ada 12 kerang dalam semangkuk mi.
My mom and dad kept arguing even at the restaurant.
Ibu dan ayah terus berdebat bahkan di restoran.
I was on pins and needles,
Aku masih gelisah,
so I kept counting the clams in the noodles.
jadi, aku terus menghitung kerang dalam mi.
There were 12 of them. "There are so many of them.
Ada 12 kerang. "Ada banyak sekali.
Dad, there are 12 clams in this."
Ayah, ada 12 kerang di dalam mangkuk."
I wanted to say that,
Aku ingin katakan itu,
but my mom kept lashing out at my dad nonstop.
tapi ibuku mengkritik ayahku tanpa henti.
What was so important?
Apa yang begitu penting?
My dad said nothing and just kept quiet.
Ayahku diam saja.
That got her riled up even more,
Itu membuatnya lebih kesal.
so she said whatever came to mind.
Dia katakan apa pun yang muncul di benaknya.
And I kept counting the clams over and over.
Aku terus menghitung kerangnya berulang-ulang.
No matter how many times I counted, there were 12 of them.
Hasilnya tetap, ada 12 kerang.
What do you think...
Menurutmu apa...
was so important to my dad?
yang begitu penting bagi ayahku?
You said you're a god.
Kau bilang kau dewa.
Then grant me a wish.
Kabulkan satu permintaanku.
Let me meet my dad.
Izinkan aku bertemu ayahku.
I want to ask him why he had to dump all of these burdens on me
Aku mau bertanya kenapa dia berikan beban itu padaku.
and if he's been able to sleep at night
Apa dia bisa tidur nyenyak
and eat well since leaving me. I want to tell him to take them all from me.
dan makan enak setelah meninggalkanku.
He couldn't even save his own daughter.
Dia bahkan tak bisa selamatkan putrinya.
How is he going to save the world? If I could ask him that question...
Kok bisa menyelamatkan dunia? Jika bisa kutanyakan...
I'd have nothing more to wish for.
aku tak punya permintaan lagi.
-Have you tried to look for him? -No, I haven't.
- Apa kau pernah mencarinya? - Tidak, belum.
What if I do and find him here in Korea?
Bagaimana jika aku menemukannya di Korea?
If he never visited us, even though he's been here the whole time...
Jika dia tak pernah mengunjungi kami walau dia di sini...
then what should I do?
bagaimana?
How do you feel now?
Bagaimana perasaanmu?
Is that really your wish?
Apa itu sungguh keinginanmu?
Meeting your dad and telling him everything you've wanted to say to him?
Bertemu ayahmu dan mengatakan semua yang ingin kau katakan.
I think so.
Kurasa begitu.
What is it?
Ada apa?
Nothing.
Tak ada.
This is nice.
Ini bagus.
What's nice?
Apanya?
Do you know why people get married?
Kau tahu kenapa orang menikah?
It's because they don't want to part ways after a whole day of fun together.
Karena tak mau berpisah setelah seharian bersenang-senang bersama.
But we live together, so we don't have to part ways.
Tapi kita hidup bersama, jadi, tak perlu berpisah.
It's nice to live together.
Senang bisa hidup bersama.
Do gods get married too?
Apa dewa juga menikah?
I could say they do. But then again, I could say they don't.
Iya. Tapi juga bisa dibilang tidak.
What does that mean?
Apa artinya?
You can get married if you want to.
Kau bisa menikah jika mau.
But it's neither exclusive, nor does it have any binding power.
Tapi itu tak eksklusif dan tak mengikat.
What? Come again? If that's the case,
Apa? Coba ulangi? Jika begitu,
can both parties cheat on each other whenever they want to?
bisakah keduanya saling selingkuh kapan saja?
It's very freewheeling.
Itu sangat bebas.
That's why people are unsure who Lady Yuhwa's mother is.
Makanya orang tak yakin siapa ibu Nona Yuhwa.
Who is Lady Yuhwa?
Siapa Nona Yuhwa?
Your daughter.
Putrimu.
Ju-mong's mother and King Yuri's maternal grandmother.
Ibu Ju-mong dan neneknya Raja Yuri.
You're King Yuri's maternal grandfather, so she's your wife.
Kau kakek Raja Yuri, jadi, dia istrimu.
-I've never been married. -Whatever.
- Aku belum menikah. - Terserah.
Don't even try to pretend.
Jangan pura-pura.
You look like you're sulking.
Tampaknya kau kesal.
What did you just say?
Apa katamu?
Give me a glass of water.
Ambilkan aku air.
I mean, why do laws and systems exist?
Lalu kenapa hukum dan sistem ada?
Their power comes from their legally binding force.
Kekuatan mereka berasal dari kekuatan mengikat mereka.
What? "Freewheeling"? Gosh, is it like Animal Kingdom or what?
Apa? Bebas?
Is it because they're all Mr. and Ms. Nature?
Apa karena semua Tuan dan Nyonya Alam?
By any chance,
Omong-omong...
is polygamy practiced in the world of gods?
apa poligami dipraktikkan di dunia para dewa?
How did you know?
Kok kau tahu?
There are even some goddesses who have many husbands.
Ada dewi yang punya banyak suami.
-Are you serious? -Isn't it obvious?
- Kau serius? - Bukankah sudah jelas?
We neither grow old nor die.
Tak bisa menua atau mati.
How can we be expected to be faithful to only one person?
Bagaimana kami bisa setia hanya kepada satu orang?
What's wrong?
Ada apa?
Then in your case,
Lalu kau sendiri...
how many times have you been married?
berapa kali kau menikah?
-I told you I've never been married. -Then what about Lady Yuhwa...
- Kubilang aku belum pernah menikah. - Lalu Nona Yuhwa...
Come to your senses, woman.
Sadarlah, Perempuan.
Get me another glass of water.
Ambilkan air lagi.
One more glass.
Satu gelas lagi.
Look.
Dengar.
What are you doing now?
Kau sedang apa?
Can't you see?
Kau tak lihat?
I don't want to go to bed.
Aku tak ingin tidur.
What?
Apa?
If you don't want to go to bed,
Jika kau tak ingin tidur...
what do you want to do?
kau mau apa?
Namsuri said he's working all night.
Namsuri bilang dia kerja semalaman.
Great timing.
Waktu yang tepat.
-So? -So...
- Jadi? - Jadi…
I'd like to...
Aku ingin…
I'd like to watch some TV with you.
Aku mau menonton TV bersamamu.
-TV? -Sit down.
- TV? - Duduklah.
He looks unfamiliar.
Dia tampak asing.
He's new.
Dia baru.
Introduce him to me. Who is he? Hey, what's your name?
Perkenalkan dia kepadaku. Hai, siapa namamu?
-Hey, come here. -Yes.
- Hai, kemarilah. - Ya.
-Have we met? -No.
- Kita pernah bertemu? - Tidak.
-So-a. -Yes?
- So-a. - Ya?
What did you see this time?
Apa yang kau lihat kali ini?
-I read your diary. -What?
- Kubaca buku harianmu. - Apa?
What did you say?
Apa katamu?
Not everyone gets to lie on my lap.
Tak semua bisa berbaring di pangkuanku.
Why would you read someone else's diary?
Kenapa baca buku harian orang lain?
I thought it was written for me
Kupikir itu ditulis untukku
two decades ago.
dua dekade lalu.
What?
Apa?
It's titled Daddy's Lap.
Judulnya Pangkuan Ayah.
"Daddy's lap is mine.
"Pangkuan Ayah milikku.
Go away, Sang-yu.
Pergilah, Sang-yu.
Daddy's lap is mine.
Pangkuan ayah milikku.
Curse you, Sang-yu." Do you call that a poem?
Terkutuk kau, Sang-yu. " Kau sebut itu puisi?
You said you were an amazing poet when you were little.
Kau bilang kau penyair hebat saat kecil.
-Isn't there a rerun of The Divine Dinner? -Hey, I know what you're thinking.
Bukankah ada tayangan ulang The Divine Dinner?
If I had your amazing powers,
Jika aku punya kekuatan luar biasa milikmu...
I'd take charge of cooking until the day I leave.
aku akan bertugas memasak sampai aku pergi.
When do you plan to leave?
Kapan pergi?
A messenger will come.
Kurir akan datang.
It could be tomorrow, right?
Bisa jadi besok, bukan?
We don't know when we will have to part ways.
Kita tak tahu kapan kita berpisah.
When I was an intern,
Saat aku jadi pekerja magang...
I saw a number of terminally ill patients and their families,
aku melihat sejumlah pasien sakit parah dan keluarga mereka.
and I felt guilty for some reason whenever I saw them.
Aku merasa bersalah tiap kali kulihat mereka.
I obviously couldn't fully understand how they were feeling.
Jelas aku tak bisa memahami perasaan mereka.
I just tried to comfort them the way I was taught to,
Aku mencoba menghibur mereka seperti yang diajarkan kepadaku,
but I had no idea what was really going through their minds.
tapi aku tak tahu apa yang sungguh dipikirkan benak mereka.
It might have been a better idea to just cry with them.
Mungkin lebih baik menangis bersama mereka.
But instead, I poured out a bunch of irresponsible words.
Malah aku katakan kata-kata yang tak bertanggung jawab.
Still, I learned something.
Namun aku belajar sesuatu.
I got to see people preparing for goodbyes...
Aku melihat orang bersiap berpisah...
and what gets left after those goodbyes.
dan yang tersisa setelah perpisahan itu.
Whether it's for the rest of the family or for themselves,
Entah itu untuk keluarga atau untuk mereka sendiri,
they would find a reason why they must not wither away,
mereka akan mencari alasan kenapa mereka tak menyerah...
and their wandering minds...
dan pikiran mereka yang mengembara
would find a place to stay in the end.
akan mencari tempat bernaung pada akhirnya.
Can I ask you something?
Boleh aku bertanya?
What about you?
Bagaimana denganmu?
How do you cope?
Bagaimana kau menghadapinya?
I have 40 to 50 years left to live at most.
Aku punya 40 hingga 50 tahun lagi untuk hidup.
But your life never ends.
Tapi hidupmu tak pernah berakhir.
Can I...
Bolehkah...
be greedy?
aku serakah?
Can I ask you to remember me...
Bolehkah aku memintamu mengingatku...
for as long as you can?
selama yang kau bisa?
What are you doing?
Apa yang kau lakukan?
You're up.
Kau bangun.
I woke up early and had nothing to do,
Aku bangun lebih awal dan tak ada pekerjaan,
so I watched a rerun of The Divine Dinner.
jadi, kutonton tayangan ulang The Divine Dinner.
And?
Lalu?
And what?
Apa?
Come on.
Ayolah.
Are you making breakfast for me?
Apa kau membuat sarapan untukku?
I found a guy who makes breakfast for me.
Aku menemukan pria yang membuat sarapan untukku.
-I'm only doing this because I'm hungry. -Really?
Ini karena aku lapar.
Then I'll just go back to sleep.
Maka aku akan kembali tidur.
I don't usually eat breakfast.
Aku tak biasa sarapan.
Sit down.
Duduklah.
My stomach gets upset if I have breakfast.
Perutku sakit jika aku sarapan.
I'll go wash first
Aku mandi dulu
so that I can pay my respects to this special breakfast.
agar bisa menghormati sarapan spesial ini.
He's so cute, but I can't tell him.
Dia sangat manis, tapi aku tak bisa katakan.
He'd get so angry.
Dia akan sangat marah.
Should I just try?
Haruskah aku coba?
What if he turns into something else?
Bagaimana jika dia berubah?
This is too much for breakfast.
Ini terlalu berlebihan untuk sarapan.
Who's going to eat all this food?
Siapa akan makan semua ini?
Do you know that food waste--
- Apa kau tahu sampah makanan... - Bilang saja kau senang.
Have a seat.
Duduklah.
Let's eat.
Ayo makan.
Dig in.
Makanlah.
So, this is how it feels...
Jadi, ini rasanya...
when someone cooks for you.
seseorang memasak untukmu.
Eat.
Makan.
Let's eat.
Ayo makan.
I locked the door but couldn't find any flower pots.
Aku mengunci pintunya, tapi tak bisa menemukan pot.
He came to give me back the keys. He couldn't find the pot.
Dia mengembalikan kunci karena tak bisa temukan potnya.
I thought hard about what to do.
Aku berpikir keras.
You wouldn't be coming to the clinic for a while.
Kau tak akan ke klinik untuk sementara.
I couldn't decide whether I should have them delivered to you
Aku tak bisa memutuskan apa aku harus kukirimkan
or ask you to meet up with me.
atau memintamu menemuiku.
-You can't do that. -I know. That's why I came here.
- Kau tak bisa lakukan itu. - Ya.
-Would you like some tea? -It's too early for tea.
- Kau mau teh? - Ini terlalu pagi untuk teh.
There is no such rule.
Tidak ada aturan seperti itu.
In my house, there is.
Di rumahku ada.
We don't drink tea in the morning here.
Kami tak minum teh di pagi hari.
We have breakfast instead. If you haven't eaten, have some breakfast.
Kami sarapan.
Mr. Shin is very busy--
Pak Shin sangat sibuk...
Then I shall join you for breakfast.
Aku akan ikut sarapan.
Goodness gracious.
Astaga.
Ms. Yun, you're a good cook.
- Nona Yun, kau koki hebat. - Masakanku.
She didn't do anything.
Dia tak melakukan apa pun.
I made all the food.
Aku buat semua makanan ini.
-Is that so? -I guess you don't know.
- Benarkah? - Kurasa kau tidak tahu.
She's a terrible cook.
Dia koki yang buruk.
And she can sleep anywhere.
Dan dia bisa tidur di mana saja.
She falls asleep right away.
Dia akan langsung tertidur.
That's why...
Karena itu...
I always have to...
aku selalu harus...
carry her to her bed, every night.
membawanya ke ranjangnya setiap malam.
She's such a handful.
Dia sulit diatur.
There's more.
Ada lagi.
She can't even turn on the light at the door.
Dia tak bisa menyalakan lampu pintu.
That's why I always turn it on for her.
Aku selalu menyalakannya untuknya.
Also, she rarely cleans. That's why I clean her place for her.
Dia juga jarang bersih-bersih.
I take a warm bath every morning.
Aku mandi air hangat setiap pagi.
It doesn't suit her,
Tidak cocok untuknya, tapi dia jadi sangat malu
whenever she sees me naked.
setiap kali melihatku telanjang.
Hey, look.
Hai, dengar.
Am I wrong?
Apa aku salah?
You said you just can't get used to it.
Kau bilang kau tak bisa terbiasa.
Hey, please.
Aku mohon.
Am I wrong?
Apa aku salah?
Did you say you never get sick of it?
Kau bilang kau tak pernah bosan?
Let's eat.
Ayo makan.
You two live together,
Kalian tinggal bersama.
so you seem to know a lot about each other.
Kalian saling mengenal.
Oh, right. Ms. Yun.
Benar. Nona Yun?
About your new landlord...
Soal pemilik barumu...
It's me.
Itu aku.
Are you serious?
Kau serius?
Is it really true?
Sungguh?
Is that why we got our rent and deposit lowered?
Apa itu sebabnya sewa dan deposit kami turun?
I told you...
Sudah kubilang...
that I'd just buy the whole building.
aku beli saja gedungnya.
I told you that I have a lot of money.
Sudah kubilang aku punya banyak uang.
A building owner...
Pemilik gedung...
Thank you so much.
Terima kasih banyak.
I'm hugely indebted to you.
Aku berutang budi padamu.
Not at all.
Tidak sama sekali.
I did it for all the tenants in my building.
Aku melakukannya untuk semua penyewa di gedungku.
Chairman Shin has been too greedy, so they've all been pretty stressed out.
Presdir Shin terlalu rakus,
Thank you very much.
Terima kasih banyak.
I'm so relieved now.
Aku lega sekali sekarang.
Please don't mention it.
Jangan begitu.
I should be a good landlord.
Aku harus jadi pemilik yang baik.
You're already such a wonderful landlord--
Kau sudah jadi pemilik yang baik...
I'm a king!
Aku seorang raja!
I am...
Aku...
a king.
seorang raja.
I like how the house shows traces of time.
Aku suka rumah ini menunjukkan jejak waktu.
I was born in this house.
Aku lahir di rumah ini.
Although half of it is owned by the bank now.
Kini separuhnya dimiliki bank.
It's okay.
Tak apa-apa.
It's all right.
Tidak apa-apa.
Stay still.
Jangan bergerak.
-Ms. Yun. -Yes?
- Nona Yun? - Ya?
Are you sure we never met in the past?
Yakin kita tak pernah bertemu?
Yes, as far as I remember.
Seingatku begitu.
Then why do I keep...
Lalu kenapa aku terus…
How dare you try to pull this trick?
Beraninya kau melakukan tipuan?
Have a seat. In my house, we drink tea after each meal.
Duduklah.
That's the rule here.
Itu aturan di sini.
Make some tea for us.
Buatkan teh.
What is this? He's trying hard to look patriarchal, but it's so awkward.
Apa ini?
What a heavenly sight.
Benar-benar pemandangan astral.
The God of Water, who's the ruler of the divine world,
Dewa Air, penguasa dunia suci,
and a demigod.
dan manusia setengah dewa.
Why did he get changed?
Kenapa dia ganti baju?
I want it in my cup.
Aku ingin itu di cangkirku.
I have my own cup. I call it Yongyong.
Aku punya cangkir sendiri. Kusebut Yongyong.
A master and his servant are both drawn on it.
Ada gambar tuan dan pelayannya.
The design is very artistic.
Desainnya sangat artistik.
I worked a part-time job
Aku kerja paruh waktu
and bought it for her.
dan membelinya untuknya.
I want this in my cup.
Aku mau ini di cangkirku.
Well, you should just drink it in this today.
Minumlah pakai ini hari ini.
I'll do that if that's what you want.
Akan kulakukan jika itu maumu.
I should go wash the dishes.
Aku harus mencuci piring.
You two look lovely together.
Kalian cocok.
Then why are you here?
Lalu kenapa di sini?
The keys?
Kuncinya?
That childish trick of yours won't even faze me.
Trik kekanakanmu itu tak akan menggangguku.
Even if you can't outdo your rival,
Jika tak bisa menang,
he may reveal his shortcomings if you keep throwing jabs at him.
lawan bisa mengungkap kelemahannya jika terus dipukul.
Like I've told you,
Seperti kataku...
waiting is my specialty.
menunggu adalah keahlianku.
You'll spend the rest of your life realizing how futile that wait is,
Kau akan habiskan sisa hidupmu menyadari betapa sia-sianya menunggu.
and you'll think that this lifetime of yours is an epic fail.
Kau akan berpikir hidup kekalmu adalah kegagalan besar.
I envy that confidence of yours.
Aku iri dengan kepercayaanmu.
I'm a king.
Aku raja.
Ms. Yun told me that I should never be intimidated by others' backgrounds.
Kata Nona Yun, aku tak boleh terintimidasi latar belakang orang lain.
That's pointless.
Itu tidak ada gunanya.
Anyhow, time is on my side.
Bagaimanapun, waktu ada di pihakku.
And come to think of it, money is also on my side.
Kalau dipikirkan, uang juga di pihakku.
-I'm a king. -I own a building.
- Aku raja. - Aku pemilik gedung.
What would be more powerful between money and a king here?
Apa yang lebih kuat antara uang dan raja?
-Shall we see? -What?
- Kita lihat saja? - Apa?
-Ms. Yun. -Yes?
- Nona Yun? - Ya?
You've forgotten about the shift at the farm in two days, right?
Kau lupa sif di peternakan dua hari lagi, ya?
I'm sorry.
Maaf.
This isn't good.
Ini tidak bagus.
We are friends, but we also have a contract.
Kita berteman, tapi kita juga punya kontrak.
I'm really sorry. I've been all over the place.
Maafkan aku. Banyak yang kupikirkan.
Well... You'll leave in the afternoon, right?
Baik.
-Then I'll also-- -Where do you think you're going?
- Aku juga... - Ke mana kau?
I don't know what this is about, but you can't take her, no matter what.
Aku tak tahu apa ini, tapi kau tak bisa membawanya.
She's indebted to me.
Dia berutang kepadaku.
When she broke the land contract, she agreed to pay the penalty.
Saat batal jual tanah, dia setuju membayar denda.
She must earn money and pay me back
Dia harus mencari uang dan membayarku
in order to fulfill her obligations and end the contract.
untuk memenuhi kewajibannya dan akhiri kontrak.
I'll see you then.
Sampai bertemu lagi.
This is all because you didn't allow me to sell the land.
Ini karena kau tak mengizinkanku menjual tanah.
Give me some money.
Beri aku uang.
Our servant didn't sell her land to that halfie,
Pelayan kita tak menjual tanah pada makhluk itu,
so she now has to pay him a penalty.
jadi, dia harus bayar penalti.
She owes him money because of us, so--
Dia berutang karena kita, jadi...
What a joke.
Dasar payah.
It sounds like that was Habaek on the phone.
Terdengar seperti Habaek.
It looks like Mr. Shin is doing a great job.
Sepertinya Pak Shin bekerja dengan baik.
He's doing what the life coach told him to do.
Dia melakukan perintah pelatih.
I don't want to hear that name yet.
Aku tak mau mendengar namanya.
Try not to bring him up.
Jangan sebut dia.
No, I'll keep talking about him until you get sick of it.
Tidak, aku akan terus membicarakannya sampai kau bosan.
What is this about?
Ada apa ini?
I heard that women dream of having breakfast
Kudengar wanita memimpikan sarapan buatan pria
made by men they love.
yang mereka cintai.
Only foolish humans would dream of such a thing.
Hanya manusia yang memimpikan hal itu.
Try to think like a human for a few minutes, then.
Cobalah berpikir seperti manusia.
Shouldn't it be with the man I love, though?
Bukankah seharusnya pria yang kucintai?
How many more steps do I have to take? 50 or 100?
Berapa langkah lagi? Apakah 50 atau 100?
Will I be able to get there?
Apa aku bisa sampai ke sana?
Get out. I'm going to take a shower.
Keluar. Aku mau mandi.
All right, then.
Baiklah.
She's the most difficult woman to deal with.
Dia wanita paling sulit dihadapi.
I know that, of course.
Aku tahu itu, tentu.
Habaek.
Habaek.
Not today.
Tidak hari ini.
My schedule is fully packed.
Jadwalku padat.
I'll call you.
Aku akan meneleponmu.
When I return to the divine realm,
Saat aku kembali ke alam suci,
I'll be sure to turn one of you into a saury
aku akan mengubahmu jadi ikan
and the other one into a sparrow.
dan satunya menjadi burung pipit.
Yes, My Lord.
Ya, Tuan.
Money. Are you earning a lot of it?
Uang. Kau dapat uang banyak?
Pardon me? Yes.
Apa? Ya.
My duck boat is swamped with customers now.
Perahu bebekku dibanjiri pelanggan.
Oh, right. Lord Judong called.
Benar. Tuan Judong menelepon.
What? Where is he?
Apa? Di mana dia?
-Why isn't he back yet? -He'll be back soon.
- Kenapa belum kembali? - Segera.
He said you shouldn't go anywhere and wait for him.
Dia bilang Tuan tunggu saja dia.
But why did he call you?
Kenapa dia meneleponmu?
He could've called me.
Seharusnya aku.
He said Lady Mura told him not to call you
Katanya Nona Mura melarangnya karena Tuan terus meminta uang.
How dare she.
Beraninya dia.
He is...
Dia adalah...
He's the one who saved me.
Dia yang menyelamatkanku.
It was him.
Itu dia.
But...
Tapi...
What? What are you talking about now?
Apa?
What was that about?
Apa itu tadi?
"He saved me." That was all good.
"Dia menyelamatkanku." Itu bagus.
But she said, "But."
Tapi dia bilang, "Tapi."
That's what keeps bothering me.
Itu yang menggangguku.
I'm sorry I'm a bit late.
Maaf, aku agak telat.
My co-worker who has the shift after mine was late.
Rekan kerja setelah aku terlambat.
-Namsuri. -Yes?
- Namsuri. - Ya?
I keep having the same dream,
Aku terus punya mimpi yang sama, itu menggangguku.
I never hear the most important part.
Aku tak pernah dengar bagian terpenting.
Is there anything I can do?
Ada yang bisa kulakukan?
I don't know.
Entahlah.
Why? Gosh!
Kenapa? Astaga!
-Hey, what's up? -Is everything all right with you?
Hai, apa kabar?
What's this about?
Ada apa ini?
It sounds like you want there to be some problems.
Sepertinya kau ingin ada masalah.
My friend, you've become bitter after a bad relationship.
Temanku, kau sengsara setelah hubungan yang buruk.
My relationship wasn't bad.
Hubunganku tidak buruk.
Then there must be something wrong with your dating style.
Pasti ada yang salah dengan gaya kencanmu.
You love in order to say goodbye? That's nonsense.
Mencintai untuk berpisah? Omong kosong.
Some people say they break up even though they love each other.
Ada yang putus meski saling mencintai.
But no one loves in order to break up.
Tapi tak ada yang cinta untuk putus.
You left out "properly."
Kau kurang "dengan benar."
It's to break up properly.
Untuk putus dengan benar.
-I have to go. -Hold on.
- Aku harus pergi. - Tunggu.
How's he doing? That boyfriend of yours who saved you.
Apa kabar kekasihmu yang menyelamatkanmu?
Who is in such a ridiculous relationship?
Siapa yang menjalin hubungan konyol begitu?
You know it won't work. Why are you trying so hard?
Kau tahu tak berhasil. Kenapa berusaha keras?
Do you have to pay interest when you borrow money?
Apa kau harus membayar bunga saat meminjam uang?
I'll pay you a lot of interest when I'm back in the Land of Water.
Aku akan membayarmu saat aku kembali ke Negeri Air.
Who needs money in the divine realm?
Siapa yang butuh uang di alam suci?
I'm not talking about money.
Maksudku bukan uang.
Tell me if you need anything.
Katakan jika kau butuh sesuatu.
Can you even give up the throne for me?
Bisa kau berikan takhtamu padaku?
It's not like I want that.
Aku tak mau itu.
I might not like you, but I don't want that kind of tragedy.
Aku mungkin tak suka kau, tapi aku tak ingin tragedi semacam itu.
I'd like you to be around for a long time.
Aku ingin kau bersamaku untuk waktu yang lama.
So, is that a no?
Kau tidak mau?
I could give you anything, be it money or diamonds.
Aku bisa memberimu apa saja, baik uang atau berlian.
But Mura doesn't like that.
Tapi Mura tak suka itu.
I listen to my girl.
Aku mendengarkan pacarku.
On the internet,
Di Internet,
people call someone like you "a pushover."
orang menyebut orang sepertimu penurut.
I don't have a problem with that.
Aku tak keberatan.
I'm off.
Aku pergi.
Hold on.
Tunggu.
-I have something to ask you. -What?
- Aku mau bertanya sesuatu. - Apa?
What is it?
Apa itu?
What is...
Seperti apa...
Mura like?
Mura?
Did you... meet Habaek?
Apa kau bertemu Habaek?
Did you attack his weak point?
Apa kau menyerang bagian terlemahnya?
It's not like that.
Bukan seperti itu.
Good. Show him how superior you are
Bagus. Tunjukkan kepadanya betapa superiornya dirimu
and how weak he is here in the human world.
dan lemahnya dia di dunia manusia.
Do you really mean it?
Kau serius?
I can't let him go like this.
Aku tak bisa diam.
He has to become a wreck.
Dia harus hancur berkeping-keping.
By the time he leaves,
Saat dia pergi,
he has to become a total wreck.
dia pasti hancur total.
You guys are so extreme.
Kalian sangat ekstrem.
Mura is the most loyal among us, as you already know.
Mura adalah yang paling setia di antara kami.
But once she turns her back on someone, that's it.
Tapi begitu dia abaikan seseorang, berakhir sudah.
Then why did you do that?
Kenapa kau melakukannya?
I'm an exception.
Aku pengecualian.
Mura and I are beyond that.
Mura dan aku lebih dari itu.
I came to the wrong person.
Aku datang ke orang yang salah.
You don't know Mura well.
Kau tak kenal baik dengan Mura.
You want to know what she really thinks, right?
Kau ingin tahu apa yang dia pikirkan?
You're really something.
Kau sungguh hebat.
You're clueless, yet you know everything.
Kau tak tahu apa-apa, tapi tahu segalanya.
You know everything, yet you don't know anything.
Tahu segalanya, tapi tak tahu apa-apa.
That's why I say I'm different from you guys.
Karena itu aku bilang aku berbeda dari kalian.
Fine, you're right.
Kau benar.
I can't figure you out.
Aku tak bisa membacamu.
No one can ever know how far you can go.
Tak ada yang tahu sejauh apa kau bisa bertindak.
If you pay me...
Jika kau membayarku,
I'll give you advice.
aku akan memberimu saran.
Those heartless punks. Are they serious?
Dasar tak berperasaan. Apa mereka serius?
Where are you going?
Mau ke mana?
Work. I have to pay off my penalty.
Kerja. Aku harus membayar denda.
I told you not to go.
Aku melarangmu pergi.
I'm sorry. He insisted on tagging along.
Maaf.
He's a good worker.
Dia pekerja yang baik.
I don't know everything about the world of gods,
Aku tak tahu apa pun tentang dunia dewa,
but considering what I've heard about Habaek,
tapi dari yang kudengar tentang Habaek,
this is unbelievable.
ini tak bisa dipercaya.
I can see why Hye-ra is so bothered.
Aku paham kenapa Hye-ra sangat terganggu.
He thinks he can pay off the penalty that way.
Dia pikir bisa pakai cara itu.
I told him I get paid for my daily work, but he wouldn't even listen.
Kubilang aku dibayar harian, tapi dia tak mau mendengarkan.
Maybe he doesn't understand daily pay.
Mungkin dia tak paham konsep upah harian.
If he didn't, I could explain to him.
Jika tidak, aku bisa jelaskan kepadanya.
But he knows what it is.
Tapi dia tahu itu.
Apparently, he read about a chairman of some company on the internet.
Rupanya dia baca tentang ketua sebuah perusahaan di internet.
A mere chairman earns 500 million won a day.
Dia dapat 500 juta won per hari.
As the emperor of all gods, my labor is invaluable and priceless.
Sebagai kaisar para dewa, pekerjaanku tak ternilai harganya.
But I'll give him the honor of putting a price on my labor.
Tapi aku memberinya kehormatan untuk membayar pekerjaanku.
Let's go.
Ayo.
So how much does the King think his labor is worth?
Menurut dia, berapa besar nilai tenaga kerja raja?
He said 50 billion won.
Itu 50 miliar won.
I see, 50 billion won?
Jadi, 50 miliar won?
He wants you to pay him the remainder after deducting the penalty.
Dia ingin kau bayar sisanya setelah dikurangi penalti.
So, 50 billion won?
Jadi, 50 miliar won?
You now seem to understand the power of money.
Kini kau paham kekuatan uang.
Your strategy was clumsy, though.
Sayang strategimu ceroboh.
Do you think I wouldn't have a chance
Apa menurutmu aku tak punya peluang
if So-a had enough money?
jika So-a punya cukup uang?
Whether she has money or not, you'll never have a place in her heart.
Entah dia punya uang atau tidak, kau tak punya tempat di hatinya.
You know too little about her.
Kau tahu terlalu sedikit tentang dia.
You think so?
Menurutmu begitu?
Then let me tell you...
Biar kuberi tahu
something you don't know.
hal yang tak kau ketahui.
I doubt there is anything.
Aku ragu itu tak ada.
There is.
Ada.
It's something you don't know because you're a god.
Sesuatu yang tak kau tahu karena kau dewa.
I know it because I'm human.
Aku tahu itu karena aku manusia.
What?
Apa?
You see...
Kau tahu...
humans are lonely from the moment they're born.
manusia itu kesepian sejak mereka lahir.
Jingeon. What is it?
Jingeon. Ada apa?
Someone came by.
Seseorang datang.
-Who? -He left something for you.
- Siapa? - Dia meninggalkan sesuatu untukmu.
-What is it? -Give me your hand.
- Apa? - Berikan tanganmu.
All right. Thank you.
Baiklah. Terima kasih.
This will be planted somewhere else. I went to the wrong spot.
Ini ditanam di tempat lain. Aku salah tempat.
-Let me help you. -It's okay.
- Biar kubantu. - Tak apa-apa.
Go check on him.
Periksa dia.
It's okay. He's not a kid.
Tak apa-apa. Dia bukan anak kecil.
The gods in the Land of Water would be shocked to hear that.
Dewa di Negeri Air akan terkejut mendengarnya.
A kid?
Anak kecil?
I'm really curious.
Aku sangat penasaran.
Is he such a big deal?
Apa dia begitu penting?
I don't know.
Entahlah.
The cave was my whole world.
Gua itu adalah duniaku.
But when Jugeollin told me about the divine world,
Tapi saat Jugeollin bercerita tentang dunia suci,
half of it was about Habaek.
separuhnya tentang Habaek.
Imprisoned in the cave, I thought of Habaek as the god of all gods.
Dikurung di gua, aku anggap Habaek dewa semua dewa.
The god of all gods?
Dewa semua dewa?
Not all gods have the same powers.
Tidak semua dewa punya kekuatan yang sama.
Some powers are only allowed to certain gods.
Ada yang hanya diizinkan untuk dewa tertentu.
Habaek could do everything.
Habaek bisa melakukan segalanya.
He was born to be king.
Dia terlahir menjadi raja.
But there are two things even Habaek can't do.
Tapi ada dua hal yang bahkan Habaek tak bisa lakukan.
He can't revive the dead.
Dia tak bisa menghidupkan yang mati.
Also...
Juga...
he doesn't have the ability I have.
dia tak punya kemampuanku.
Still, Habaek isn't intimidated by me at all.
Tetap saja, Habaek sama sekali tak terintimidasi olehku.
To be honest, I liked that about him.
Sejujurnya, aku suka dia begitu.
By the way,
Omong-omong...
are you really okay?
apa benar kau baik-baik saja?
He could go back as soon as tomorrow.
Dia bisa kembali besok.
He might be gone when you wake up.
Dia mungkin tak ada saat kau bangun.
He came back
Dia kembali
so that I can move on with my life
agar aku bisa melanjutkan hidupku
even if that happens.
meski itu terjadi.
Are you done?
Sudah selesai?
Yes.
Ya.
I want my 50 billion won. Tell him I'm giving him a discount.
Aku mau 50 miliar won. Bilang aku beri diskon.
Give me that.
Berikan itu.
What are you doing? This is so unlike you.
Sedang apa kau? Ini bukan dirimu.
Why is it unlike me?
Kenapa tak sepertiku?
You still have a lot to learn.
Banyak yang harus kau pelajari.
Shall I show you the vast scope of my chameleon-like charms?
Mau kutunjukkan pesonaku yang luar biasa seperti bunglon?
Don't.
Jangan.
Don't do that.
Jangan lakukan itu.
Hold tightly onto your chest so that your heart doesn't burst.
Pegang erat dadamu agar hatimu tak meledak.
I said, don't do it.
Kubilang jangan.
Gosh, seriously!
Yang benar saja.
How do you feel?
Bagaimana perasaanmu?
Isn't your heart racing?
Jantungmu berdetak kencang?
Browsing on the internet
Menjelajahi internet,
taught me that human women call this "sexy."
aku jadi tahu wanita sebut itu seksi.
Oh, boy.
Astaga.
Bend down, please.
Tolong menunduklah.
Why did you do that all of a sudden?
Kenapa kau melakukan itu?
-Is your heart okay? -My heart is totally fine,
- Apakah hatimu baik-baik saja? - Baik,
but I'm cringing so badly right now.
tapi aku sangat jijik sekarang.
Come here. Let's have you sit on that chair.
Kemari. Duduklah di kursi itu.
Why do you keep acting out of character today?
Kenapa kau bertingkah aneh hari ini?
Isn't it like how...
Bukankah itu seperti kau mengintipku dari belakang di depan rumah?
What?
Apa?
You said you still have 40 to 50 years left to live.
Kau bisa hidup 40 sampai 50 tahun lagi.
Then you should have...
Maka kau harus...
more memories of me...
punya lebih banyak kenanganku
so that you won't run out of them.
agar kau tak kehabisan kenangan.
You're so good at saying things like that nonchalantly.
Kau sangat santai mengatakan hal seperti itu.
I'm not saying this because I don't care.
Bukan karena aku tak peduli.
You know that I'm selfish, right?
Kau tahu aku egois, 'kan?
I'm telling you this because I'm selfish.
Kukatakan ini karena aku egois.
Try your best...
Berusahalah keras...
not to be lonely...
agar kau tak kesepian...
for as long as you can.
selama mungkin.
I will...
Aku akan...
remember you for a long time.
mengingatmu untuk waktu yang lama.
Are you mad that he didn't pay you 50 billion won?
Apa kau marah dia tak membayar 50 miliar won?
He promised you that he'll pay you five million won a day.
Dia berjanji akan memberimu lima juta won per hari.
You should work there every single day. If you work there for ten days,
Kau harus bekerja tiap hari.
you'll earn more than enough to pay off the penalty.
itu lebih dari cukup untuk dendanya.
If the two of us earn money together...
Jika kita berdua dapat uang...
That actually sounded so funny.
Itu terdengar sangat lucu.
Let's go back there tomorrow and the day after as well.
Ayo kembali ke sana besok dan lusa.
The two of us should go there every day.
Harus ke sana tiap hari.
Let's work together.
Mari bekerja bersama.
Let's stay together.
Mari tetap bersama.
All right.
Baiklah.
Where have you been?
Dari mana saja kau?
Why do you look like that?
Kenapa kau seperti itu?
Why are you here?
Kenapa di sini?
I have good news for you.
Aku punya kabar baik.
Congratulations.
Selamat.
Oh, I got this made according to the customs here.
Ini dibuat menurut adat di sini.
Such formality does matter, you know.
Formalitas semacam ini penting.
I even picked my dress to coordinate with this color.
Bahkan warna gaunku ini.
I figured I should make this much effort when I deliver this kind of news to you.
Kupikir aku harus berusaha untuk menyampaikan berita ini.
The messenger must've been busy.
Pembawa pesan pasti sibuk.
He left without even delivering this to you in person.
Dia pergi tanpa mengantarkan ini padamu.
The sixth red tide has come,
Air pasang merah keenam telah tiba,
so please get ready, Lord Habaek.
bersiaplah, Tuan Habaek.
The details are inside.
Detailnya ada di dalam.
I kept them simple
Aku buat sederhana
and wrote them in big letters so that you can read them easily.
dan dalam huruf besar agar mudah kau baca.
I'm off.
Aku pergi.
Let me say this just in case.
Aku katakan ini untuk berjaga-jaga.
You know what will happen...
Kau tahu akibatnya
if you don't return, right?
jika kau tak kembali, bukan?
Let's go in.
Ayo masuk.
Come on.
Ayolah.
Let's eat something. I'm hungry.
Ayo makan. Aku lapar.d
Come and eat.
Ayo makan.
You actually look pretty dashing even from behind.
Kau menawan bahkan dari belakang.
Come on.
Ayolah.
It's not like you didn't know. Why do you look so sad?
Seperti kau tak tahu saja. Kenapa kau terlihat sedih?
They're not asking you to return tomorrow.
Kau tak diminta kembali besok.
Why do you never tell me not to leave...
Kenapa kau tak mencegahku pergi...
even if you don't mean it?
meski tak bersungguh-sungguh?
Why is that?
Kenapa begitu?
Will you not go back if I ask you not to leave?
Lalu kau tak akan pergi?
No.
Tidak.
I can't do that.
Aku tak bisa.
See? Exactly.
Lihat? Benar sekali.
Don't sound me out like that.
Jangan bertanya begitu.
I'm not the kind of woman who holds men back.
Aku bukan tipe wanita yang menahan pria.
I'll tell you why I'm not stopping you.
Kuberi tahu kenapa tak menghentikanmu.
Think about it.
Pikirkanlah.
You're only cool because you're the king of the divine world.
Kau hanya keren karena kau raja dunia suci.
Here, you're not a king. You'll be nothing here without your powers.
Di sini tidak. Kau bukan apa-apa tanpa kekuatanmu.
You'd just be a jobless guy who likes taking warm baths.
Kau hanya pengangguran yang suka mandi air hangat.
You don't like to work. You're only interested in driving cars.
Kau tak suka kerja. Kau hanya tertarik mengendarai mobil.
I'd have to earn money and take care of you.
Aku harus bekerja dan menjagamu.
Don't watch those kinds of movies where the main characters
Jangan menonton film dengan tokoh utama
fall in love and say they don't care about money.
jatuh cinta dan katakan tak peduli soal uang.
When men behave that way, their ladies give up on them.
Saat pria begitu, wanita meninggalkan mereka.
My goodness.
Astaga.
Jeez, how is he going to be a king
Astaga, bagaimana dia akan menjadi raja
with such a sensitive heart?
dengan hati yang sensitif?
Lord Habaek.
Tuan Habaek.
-I'm back. -Why are you back so late?
- Aku pulang. - Kenapa larut?
I can work at so many places now that I have a government-issued ID.
Aku kerja di banyak tempat setelah punya KTP.
The 24-hour barbecue place asked me to cover a shift today.
Tempat barbeku 24 jam memintaku kerja hari ini.
In the afternoon, I worked on the duck boat--
Kerja di kapal bebek sore...
-Quit all your jobs. -Pardon?
- Hentikan semuanya. - Apa?
I've received the message.
Aku sudah terima pesannya.
Does that mean we're going back now?
Kita kembali sekarang?
Notify your employers in advance so that the same thing won't happen again.
Beri tahu atasanmu sebelumnya
Okay.
Baiklah.
Are you that happy?
Kau sesenang itu?
You should've seen the look on his face.
Kau harus lihat ekspresi wajahnya.
-I thought the sky was going to collapse. -Habaek must've really gotten
- Kupikir langit akan runtuh. - Habaek pasti sangat tidak kau sukai.
I even thought about not telling him about the message
Aku bahkan berpikir tak menyampaikannya
so that he'd be able to just stay here forever.
agar dia bisa tinggal di sini selamanya.
That's a bit harsh even if you only said it out of anger.
Itu terlalu keras meski kau marah.
Habaek will perish if he doesn't ascend the throne.
Habaek akan binasa jika tak naik takhta.
Will you be able to live without him?
Apa kau bisa hidup tanpanya?
And Habaek knows that too.
Habaek juga tahu itu.
This isn't about him being torn about whether he should go back.
Bukan soal dia yang bingung apa harus kembali.
So just cut him some slack.
Biarkan saja dia.
You annoy me so much.
Kau buatku kesal.
Who do you like more? Me or Habaek?
Kau lebih suka aku atau Habaek?
PLEASE BE MINE, HYE-RA
JADI MILIKKU, HYE-RA
Tell me. Who do you like more?
Katakan. Siapa yang lebih kau suka?
Hey. You...
Hai.
What?
Apa?
Me? Not Habaek?
Aku? Bukan Habaek?
Yes, I'm talking to you.
Aku bicara kepadamu.
-What's that? -What?
- Apa itu? - Apa?
PLEASE BE MINE, HYE-RA
JADI MILIKKU, HYE-RA
This?
Ini?
-It's a gift from your fans. -What?
- Ini hadiah dari fanmu. - Apa?
I heard you got angry at your fans and told them not to send gifts.
Kudengar kau marah pada fanmu dan melarang mengirim hadiah.
They're so scared of you that they've stopped sending gifts.
Mereka takut padamu hingga berhenti mengirimnya.
Well, yes.
Ya.
But, apparently, a handful of them keep sending you gifts.
Tapi beberapa dari mereka terus mengirimkan hadiah.
Mr. Kim didn't know what to do with them,
Pak Kim kebingungan,
so I told him I'd take them.
jadi, kubilang akan kubawa.
I like anything that has your face on it.
Aku suka semua yang ada wajahmu.
I'LL PROTECT YOU, HYE-RA ONE AND ONLY BEAUTY, HYE-RA
AKU PELINDUNG HYE-RA KECANTIKAN SEJATI, HYE-RA
By the way, about that gift box in your room...
Tentang kotak hadiah di kamarmu...
Yes, that one. I ate some snacks from that box.
Ya, itu. Aku makan camilan dari kotak itu.
Okay, good.
Bagus.
By the way,
Kenapa kau...
-why do you have that? -What?
punya itu?
Well...
Aku menyuruh...
I told Mr. Kim to throw everything away. He must've put it back here again.
Pak Kim membuang semuanya. Dia pasti taruh di sini lagi.
What would he know?
Apa yang dia tahu?
You're a goddess, so you don't need human beings' love.
Kau seorang dewi, jadi, kau tak butuh cinta manusia.
This pair of socks would look like a joke to you.
Kaus kaki ini akan tampak seperti lelucon bagimu.
You even looked down on my diamonds, you know.
Kau bahkan meremehkan berlianku.
Right.
Benar.
Only lowly human beings care about these stupid things.
Hanya manusia rendahan yang peduli akan hal-hal bodoh ini.
There. I'll take it.
Nah. Aku ambil ini.
I like it because it has your face on it.
Aku suka karena ada wajahmu.
What are you doing?
Apa yang kau lakukan?
Where are you going?
Mau ke mana?
Do you want to come with me?
Mau ikut denganku?
This is it.
Ini dia.
The place where I made a foolish mistake.
Tempat aku membuat kesalahan bodoh.
It was 11:35 p.m. on December 20, 2004.
Pukul 23.35 tanggal 20 Desember 2004.
I even remember the exact time.
Aku bahkan ingat waktunya.
After my dad left,
Setelah ayahku pergi,
I studied very hard in order to become happy.
aku belajar sangat keras untuk menjadi bahagia.
It was just like what you told me.
Seperti ucapanmu.
I only believed what I wanted to believe.
Aku hanya percaya yang ingin kupercayai.
Like you said, it made things much easier to cope with.
Seperti katamu, itu membuat segalanya lebih mudah diatasi.
Your dad abandoned us. Just think of it that way.
Ayahmu menelantarkan kita.
Had I not done that, I would've had to spend my entire youth
Jika aku tak begitu, aku habiskan masa mudaku
trying to understand my dad.
untuk memahami ayahku.
But...
Tapi...
even my mom was struggling to endure the hardship behind my back.
bahkan ibuku berjuang menanggung kesulitan di belakangku.
I really hated her.
Aku sangat membencinya.
I was doing a good job of hanging in there even after my mom died.
Aku mampu bertahan bahkan setelah ibuku meninggal.
Even that day,
Bahkan pada hari itu...
I had a perfectly normal day at school.
aku mengalami hari yang normal di sekolah.
But, suddenly...
Tapi tiba-tiba...
this strange feeling took me over.
muncul perasaan aneh.
It suddenly came to me,
Tiba-tiba aku sadar,
instantly took over my thoughts,
pikiranku penuh dengan hal itu...
and led me to this bridge.
dan membawaku ke jembatan ini.
"Why didn't God save any love for me...
"Kenapa Tuhan tak menyimpan cinta untukku...
when there's so much love in this world?
padahal begitu banyak cinta di dunia?
Why did God leave me out?
Kenapa Tuhan meninggalkanku?
Why...
Kenapa...
Why does God only hate me?"
Kenapa Tuhan hanya membenciku? "
I told myself I'd think God still loves me
Aku meyakinkan diri Tuhan masih mencintaiku
if my dad picked up...
jika ayahku mengangkatnya...
and that I'd think...
dan aku berpikir
God really hates me
Tuhan sungguh membenciku
-if he didn't pick up. -Dad...
- jika dia tak menjawabnya. - Ayah...
That was my conclusion.
Itu kesimpulanku.
Please...
Kumohon...
The person you are trying to reach is unavailable. Please leave a message.
Nomor yang Anda hubungi tidak aktif. Tinggalkan pesan.
My dad's cell phone never turned on again.
Ponsel ayahku tak pernah hidup lagi.
So I decided to take revenge on him in the most terrible way.
Jadi, kuputuskan untuk membalas dendam dengan cara yang paling buruk.
I'm going to make you regret this for the rest of your life.
Aku akan membuatmu menyesal selama sisa hidupmu.
Of course, it just ended up becoming my most embarrassing memory.
Tentu saja, itu hanya menjadi memoriku yang paling memalukan.
And once again...
Sekali lagi...
I have to say goodbye to someone I love.
aku harus berpamitan dengan orang yang kucintai.
I wanted to know how I really feel.
Aku ingin tahu bagaimana perasaanku.
I wanted to know...
Aku ingin tahu...
if I'd still feel like I did when I jumped from this bridge...
jika aku masih merasa seperti saat melompat dari jembatan ini...
or...
atau...
if I've matured into a real adult.
jika aku sudah jadi dewasa.
I wanted to check.
Aku ingin memeriksanya.
Thank you...
Terima kasih...
for loving me.
telah mencintaiku.
Let's go home and eat something.
Ayo kita pulang dan makan.
So this is better than the other proposal.
Ini lebih baik dari proposal lain.
Hey, I've been giving it some thought, and I can't figure out your intentions.
Hai, aku sudah memikirkannya.
What happened to you?
Apa yang terjadi padamu?
"A decent human being"?
Manusia yang baik?
I'm a human being who has 22 pairs of autosomes
Aku manusia dengan 22 pasang autosom
and one pair of X chromosomes.
dan satu pasang kromosom X.
But you told me to become a human being,
Tapi kau suruh aku jadi manusia,
so I thought there could be a hidden message behind that.
kupikir ada pesan tersembunyi di baliknya.
So I even ended up studying the DNA sequence.
Aku bahkan mempelajari urutan DNA.
Don't you see the steam coming off my head?
Kau tak lihat ada uap dari kepalaku?
And I took countless pills to get rid of my headache.
Aku minum banyak pil untuk menghilangkan sakit kepala.
It's been a while since I graduated, so I forgot everything!
Sudah lama aku lulus, jadi, aku lupa segalanya!
Why did you make me study everything again?
Kenapa paksa aku mempelajari semuanya lagi?
Ja-ya.
Ja-ya.
What's wrong with you?
- Ada apa denganmu? - Dia meremehkanku.
I know he goes to church, but why is he trying to make me study?
Aku tahu dia ke gereja,
Did my grandpa put you up to this?
Apa kakekku menyuruhmu?
That's what happened, right? How much did he pay you?
Itu yang terjadi? Berapa banyak dia membayarmu?
Did you receive money?
Kau dapat uang, bukan?
Hey, say something. You got money from him, right?
Bicara. Kau dapat uang darinya, bukan?
How much did you get? Did you get a lot?
Berapa? Kau dapat banyak?
Let go!
Lepaskan.
Are you stupid?
Apa kau bodoh?
What does the DNA sequence
Apa kaitan DNA dengan mengusir Nona Yun dari gedung?
That's exactly what I want to ask you. Do you have feelings for So-a?
Itu yang ingin kutanyakan.
Ja-ya.
Ja-ya.
You should quit your job.
Kau sebaiknya berhenti bekerja.
Your job requires intelligence,
Pekerjaanmu membutuhkan kecerdasan,
but it also requires you to have a big heart.
tapi juga menuntut hati yang besar.
What?
Apa?
I'm not interested in becoming a sexy celebrity.
Aku tak tertarik jadi selebritas seksi.
You should learn to have a bigger heart and become a decent human being.
Kau harus belajar berbesar hati
"A bigger heart"?
Besar hati?
"A decent human being"?
Manusia yang baik?
Why is the list getting longer?
Kenapa daftarnya makin panjang?
THE ONE AND ONLY, HYE-RA
SATU-SATUNYA, HYE-RA
What's wrong? Is this your first time seeing me topless?
Apa yang salah?
Is that towel from one of my fans as well?
Apa handuk itu dari penggemarku juga?
Yes, it's really nice. It has your name on it.
Ya, ini sangat bagus. Ada namamu di sini.
My gosh, what's wrong with him?
Astaga, ada apa dengannya?
I don't even have a lot of them.
Aku bahkan tak punya banyak.
HYE-RA IS MINE
HYE-RA MILIKKU
What are you doing?
Apa yang kau lakukan?
Hey, this is so moisturizing.
Hai, ini sangat melembabkan.
You...
Kau...
What?
Apa?
What's wrong?
Ada apa?
-Is that-- -Are you angry
- Apa itu... - Apa kau marah
-because I'm using these gifts from-- -No.
- aku memakai hadiah dari... - Tidak.
-Why would I be angry? -Didn't you say you hate...
- Kenapa marah? - Bukankah kau benci
-getting gifts from humans? -Yes, I hate them. They're filthy.
dapat hadiah dari manusia?
Just tell your fans that they can send you gifts again.
Beri tahu fanmu mereka bisa kirim hadiah lagi.
Why are you being so stubborn for no reason?
Kenapa kau keras kepala tanpa alasan?
-It's all pointless. -What do you know?
- Itu tak berguna. - Apa yang kau tahu?
I didn't know anything until a moment ago,
Aku tak tahu apa pun beberapa saat lalu,
but now I do.
tapi kini aku tahu.
The design isn't that pretty.
Desainnya tidak cantik.
Do I have 50 or 100 more steps left?
Ada sisa 50 atau 100 langkah lagi?
Or could I already be inside her heart?
Atau mungkin aku sudah di dalam hatinya?
I'll try confronting your true feelings.
Akan kucoba menghadapi perasaanmu yang sebenarnya.
Get lost.
Pergilah.
Okay.
Baik.
I guess she's not that interested in a diamond ring.
Kurasa dia tak tertarik dengan cincin berlian.
Let's get her a gold ring.
Beri dia cincin emas.
A gold ring.
Cincin emas.
What brings you here at this hour? What's wrong?
Kenapa kemari selarut ini? Ada apa?
I finally solved the last puzzle.
Aku memecahkan teka-teki terakhir.
What?
Apa?
I told you that I keep seeing you in my dreams.
Kubilang aku terus melihatmu dalam mimpiku.
You're here to talk about that again?
Kau mau bahas lagi?
Come in for some food since you're here anyway.
Ayo makan karena kau di sini.
-Food isn't important right now. -No, that's all I care about right now.
Makanan tak penting sekarang.
It would've been better without you,
Akan lebih baik tanpamu,
but I can't turn away my one and only friend.
tapi aku tak bisa mengusir satu-satunya temanku.
But you really are a nuisance.
Tapi kau sungguh mengganggu.
I told you, didn't I?
Sudah kubilang, 'kan?
At first, all I could see
Awalnya, yang kulihat
was a blurry image of someone coming up to me and saying something.
hanya gambaran buram seseorang mendatangiku dan bicara.
For some reason, I felt like it was you. But guess what?
Entah kenapa, aku merasa itu kau.
A few days later, you came to me soaked in the rain, but I still
Itu menjadi kau datang basah kuyup, tapi aku masih
couldn't hear what you were saying.
tak bisa mendengarmu.
But a few days ago, I could finally hear you.
Beberapa hari lalu, akhirnya aku bisa mendengarmu.
He is...
Dia...
Yes, go on. Who are you talking about?
Lanjutkan. Siapa yang kau bicarakan?
He's the one who saved me.
Dia yang menyelamatkanku.
It was him.
Itu dia.
But...
Tapi...
So I naturally assumed it was your boyfriend.
Aku berasumsi dia adalah pacarmu.
I got angry at you for boasting about your boyfriend in my dream.
Aku marah kau sesumbar tentang pacarmu di mimpiku.
You can ask Namsuri.
Kau bisa tanya Namsuri.
Yeom-mi, hurry up and get to the point. I need to go see if the rice is ready.
Yeom-mi, cepat dan langsung ke intinya.
You said, "But."
Kau bilang, "Tapi."
-"But"? -Yes.
- "Tapi"? - Ya.
You said, "But." That means there's something unexpected.
Kau bilang, "Tapi." Artinya ada yang tak terduga.
That "But" kept bothering me.
Itu menggangguku.
But I really couldn't hear anything after that. It was so frustrating.
Tapi aku tak mendengar apa pun setelah itu. Menjengkelkan.
-Is it like The Usual Suspects? -It's more shocking than that.
- Seperti The Usual Suspects? - Lebih mengejutkan.
Anyway...
Omong-omong...
A moment ago, I was finally able to hear that part.
Sesaat lalu, aku akhirnya bisa mendengar bagian itu.
Okay, congratulations. So what did I say?
Baiklah, selamat. Jadi, apa kataku?
You said something shocking.
Kau mengatakan sesuatu yang mengejutkan.
"He's the one who saved me.
"Dia yang menyelamatkanku.
But..."
Tapi..."
He's the one who saved me.
Dia yang menyelamatkanku.
It was him.
Itu dia.
-But... -But that person who saved you...
- Tapi... - Orang yang menyelamatkanmu...
...the person who saved me.
Orang yang menyelamatkanku
is going to be the Grim Reaper who takes away my soul.
akan menjadi malaikat maut yang merenggut jiwaku.
-What? -You said the person who saved you
- Apa? - Katamu penyelamatmu
is going to be the Grim Reaper who takes away your soul.
adalah malaikat maut yang merenggut jiwamu.
It means you're going to die.
Artinya kau akan mati.
What?
Apa?
Ms. Descendant is going to die?
Nona Keturunan akan mati?
No.
Tidak.
This will be our last session.
Ini sesi terakhir kita.
Why does this have to happen to me?
Kenapa ini terjadi kepadaku?
I know that you've decided to use the power you need
Aku tahu kau memutuskan memakai kekuatanmu padanya.
She said it's gods' duty to protect humans.
Katanya tugas dewa melindungi manusia.
-If you fail to ascend the throne... -What will happen if I die?
- Jika kau gagal naik takhta... - Apa yang terjadi jika aku mati?
Stop talking nonsense.
Diam.
How can I call myself a king if I can't even protect that woman?
Bagaimana aku bisa menyebut diriku raja jika tak bisa melindungi wanita itu?
How is anything more important than your life?
Apa yang lebih penting dari hidupmu?
-You're going to die? -I told you that I'll protect you.
- Kau akan mati? - Aku akan melindungimu.
You're going to disappear from my memory?
Kau akan menghilang dari ingatanku?
I love you.
Aku mencintaimu.